Guide to the Elinor Langer Collection of Josephine Herbst
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Elinor Langer collection of Josephine Herbst
1964-1994
YCAL MSS 475
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
19.5
(21 boxes) + 1 portfolio
The collection documents Elinor Langer's research and writing of the biography Josephine Herbst: The Story She Could Never Tell. The collection contains research files, correspondence, photographs, sound recordings of interviews, printed material, and other papers.
Langer, Elinor, 1939-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Elinor Langer, 2007.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 20-21 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Portfolio 22 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Associated Materials
Associated material includes the Josephine Herbst Papers (YCAL MSS 474) and other material by or relating to Josephine Herbst can be found by searching Orbis (Yale's Online Catalog).
Elinor Langer (b. 1939)
Elinor Langer is the author of the biography, Josephine Herbst: The Story She Could Never Tell.
Scope and Contents
The collection documents Elinor Langer's research and writing of the biography of American author Josephine Herbst, Josephine Herbst: The Story She Could Never Tell. The collection contains research files, correspondence, photographs, sound recordings, printed material, and other papers.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Research files, 1964-1985. II. Writings and related material, 1968-1994.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century; Audiovisual materials; Photographic prints; Sound recordings; Herbst, Josephine, 1892-1969; Langer, Elinor, 1939-
- Research files, 1964-1985; Series I; 10; (21 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains photocopies and notes created during Elinor Langer's research for her biography on Josephine Herbst. The bulk of the material is photocopies of Herbst's personal and professional papers, including her correspondence, writings and notes. There is a small amount of correspondence on Herbst between Langer and various individuals, institutions that hold Herbst material, and with individuals regarding publication permissions and the publication process. Filed at the end of the series are audio cassettes, microcassettes, and one reel-to-reel tape of interviews on Herbst between Langer and individuals.
  Arrangement
  Arranged in the order maintained by Langer.
  - Frances Wells letters to JH, 1895-1927 (Box 1)
  - Alice Herbst Hansen and John Hansen letters to JH (Box 1)
  - Helen Herbst letters to JH, 1909-1913, 2 (Box 1)
  - Helen Herbst letters to her mother, 1908-1920 (Box 1)
  - Mary Frey Herbst letters to JH, 1909-1921, 2 (Box 1)
  - William Benton Herbst letters to Mary Herbst, 1882-1900 (Box 1)
  - JH letters to Helen Herbst, 1909-1920, 2 (Box 1)
  - JH letters to Frances Herbst Wells, 1915-1916, 1958 (Box 1)
  - JH pre-1912 letters to her family and related pre-1912 miscellany (Box 1)
  - JH letters to parents,1912-1919, 6 (Box 1)
    Includes letters from Stratford, Iowa, Seattle, Berkeley
  - Jenny Frey Walsh: letters to JH, 1916-1917 (Box 1)
  - Family letters with genealogical data (Box 1)
  - JH letters and other miscellany (Box 1)
  - Pages from JH high school graduation book (Box 1)
  - Notebooks from Herbst's time in Stratford, Iowa, 1913-1914 (Box 2)
  - Early short story fragments (Box 2)
  - "Magicians and Their Apprentices," draft (Box 2)
  - "The Ground We Tread," draft (Box 2)
  - JH poems published in the Berkeley Occident, 1917-1918 (Box 2)
  - JH school records (Box 2)
  - "Following the Circle: Unmarried," draft (Box 2)
  - Iowa materials (Box 2)
  - Gynecological and other female material, including Carol Smith Rosenberg, etc. (Box 2)
  - JH letters to Edward Dahlberg, 1950-1965 (Box 2)
  - JH letters to Neal and Mary Daniels, 1955 (Box 2)
  - JH letters to Marion Greenwood (Box 2)
  - Marion Greenwood letters to Josephine Herbst (Box 2)
  - JH letters to parents, 1921-1928, 4 (Box 2)
  - John Herrmann miscellaneous, private, family, literary, and political matters (Box 2)
  - John Herrmann letters to JH, 1924-1932, 2 (Box 2)
  - John Herrmann letters to JH, 1933-1937, 2 (Box 3)
  - JH entire file to John Herrmann at Yale (Box 3)
  - JH letters to John Herrmann from the Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center (Box 3)
  - John Herrmann to Mary Lloyd (Box 3)
  - John Herrmann to Jessie Lloyd O'Connor (Box 3)
  - JH letters to Rebecca Pitts (Box 3)
  - JH letters to William Phillips (Box 3)
  - William Phillips letters to JH, 1930s (Box 3)
  - Katherine Anne Porter letters to JH, 1927-1947 (Box 3)
  - Porter to Herbst additions, commentaries, miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - JH letters to Genevieve Taggard and Bob Wolfe, 2 (Box 3)
  - Frank Walklin letters to JH, 1920-1951 (Box 3)
  - Robert Wolfe letters to JH, 1920s (Box 3)
  - JH letters to Eugene Walters, from Texas, 1950s (Box 3)
  - Frances Wells letter to JH and other miscellany, 1930s (Box 3)
  - Divorce, final papers, will, miscellaneous legal papers from Betty Davis (Box 3)
  - New York notebook, 1920s (Box 3)
  - European notebook, Berlin (Box 3)
  - The Hours of Counterfeit Bliss, Key West, Hemingway (Box 3)
  - New Republic correspondence, 1930s (Box 3)
  - Political correspondence New Masses, other magazines, invitations, miscellaneous, 1930s (Box 3)
  - Hiss-Chambers material from Allen Weinstein, and related miscellany, 2 (Box 3)
  - Spain miscellaneous JH correspondence (Box 4)
  - Spain JH correspondence with Carlos Baker re Spain, Hemingway, etc., 2 (Box 4)
  - Spanish journal (Box 4)
  - Diary, Washington, New York, 1941 (Box 4)
  - D-Day journal, 1944 (Box 4)
  - Material regarding 1940s, 1940s (Box 4)
  - JH's Will, 1950 (Box 4)
  - Journal about Jean,1951 (Box 4)
  - Journal notes, 1953 (Box 4)
  - Journal regarding Jean, 1953 (Box 4)
  - Materials relating to passport case (Box 4)
  - Bright Signal (Box 4)
  - Watcher with the Horn, 1960 (Box 4)
  - Outside Time, Regler story, Spain (Box 4)
  - Bucks County miscellaneous material (Box 4)
  - John Herrmann: "The Salesman" (Box 4)
  - John Herrmann: "Summer is Ended" (Box 4)
  - John Herrmann: "What Happens" (Box 4)
  - Phillip Stevenson letters to JH, 1930s, 1950s (Box 4)
  - Gustav Regler letters to JH (Box 4)
  - Beinecke Library miscellany (Box 4)
  - John Dos Passos letters to JH (Box 4)
  - Will Watson writing regarding Spain and correspondence with JH about it (Box 4)
  - Robles miscellany (Box 4)
  - Spain JH unpublished writings (Box 4)
  - Spain JH published writings (Box 4)
  - El Correspondence re Spain: Seldes, Tisa, Luddington and miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Spain clippings, post-Franco (Box 4)
  - Jean Garrigue materials, including correspondence with JH, 28 (Box 5)
  - Joe Freeman letters to JH, 1950s (Box 5)
  - Miscellany, 1930s (Box 5)
  - Copies of all major catalogs (Box 5)
  - James Farrell letters to JH, 1930s, 2 (Box 5)
  - FOIA/passport material (Box 6)
  - Cuba notes from trip, etc., 1930s (Box 6)
  - South America miscellaneous, 1930s (Box 6)
  - Obituaries (Box 6)
  - Miscellany, 1960s (Box 6)
  - Miranda: KAP note-file and related literary notes (Box 6)
  - JH medical materials (Box 6)
  - Mexican journals (Box 6)
  - Reviews of work, critiques, etc. (Box 6)
  - Harcourt-Brace (Box 6)
  - Nathaniel West (JH correspondence about) (Box 6)
  - Yaddo (Box 6)
  - JH late financial affairs (Box 6)
  - JH selected correspondence with Eddie Cahill, 1958 (Box 6)
  - Letters to Alfred Kazin, 1930-1965 (Box 6)
  - JH correspondence with Atlantic Monthly Press, 1959-1968 (Box 6)
  - JH letters to Claire Laining (Box 6)
  - JH selected correspondence with Hilton Kramer (Box 6)
  - JH to Stanley Burnshaw (Box 6)
  - JH selected correspondence with Saul Bellow (Box 6)
  - JH letters to Bob McAlmon, 1951-1952 (Box 6)
  - JH correspondence with Scribner's regarding memoirs (Box 6)
  - JH 1943 notes (Box 6)
  - Play outlines and related materials, 1940s (Box 6)
  - JH letters from Ann Blankanbam (Box 6)
  - 1950s diary notes and European notes, 1950s (Box 6)
  - JH 1959 material regarding Columbia "Forum," 1959 (Box 6)
  - JH 1958 writing draft, 1958 (Box 6)
  - JH manuscript 1950s (Box 6)
  - 1966 hospitalization, diary notes, 1966 (Box 6)
  - Obituary of Bravig Imbs, 1968 (Box 6)
  - ARW last book, Lucita V. Marberry (Box 6)
  - Kenneth Davis, 1959-1960 (Box 6)
  - Asch, Nathan (Box 6)
  - Cheever, John (Box 6)
  - Drafts, notes, writings by others on JH, 16 (Box 7)
  - FBI files, 5 (Box 8)
  - Reviews of book (Box 8)
  - JH/Magicians (Box 8)
  - Photographs and correspondence (Box 8)
  - Reader III (Box 8)
  - Guggenheim (Box 8)
  - "Confessions of a Female Biographer (speech given by EL)," 1989 May (Box 8)
  - Josie "Reader" correspondence (Box 8)
  - KAP-JH project correspondence (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
  - "Reader II" (Box 8)
  - Writings on Herbst by others, 4 (Box 9)
  - Langer correspondence
    - Allen, Ruth, 1973 (Box 9)
    - Atlantic, 1973-1984 (Box 9)
    - Barcharat, George, 1975-1984 (Box 9)
    - Bellow, Saul, 1973-1974 (Box 9)
    - Bernhard, Andrew, 1972-1984 (Box 9)
    - Burnshaw, Stanley, 1973-1983 (Box 9)
    - Clark, Betty Ann, 1973 (Box 9)
    - Cowley, Malcolm, 1973-1980 (Box 9)
    - Davis, Betty, 1973-1984 (Box 9)
    - Hicks, Granville, 1973-1978 (Box 9)
    - Jelinek, Estelle, 1973-1978 (Box 9)
    - Kazin, Alfred, 1973-1985 (Box 9)
    - Kramer, Hilton, 1973-1984; 2 (Box 9)
    - Mayhak, Jane, 1973-1985 (Box 9)
    - "O'Connor-Lloyd", 1973-1984 (Box 9)
    - Peck, Ruth, 1982 October 5 (Box 9)
    - Pitts, Rebecca, 1973-1978 (Box 9)
    - Sterling, John, 1979-1980 (Box 9)
    - Various libraries, 1974-1975 (Box 9)
    - Welsh, Jenny, 1973-1976 (Box 9)
    - Yale Beinecke Library, 1973-1978 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence regarding (Box 9)
    - Book business, 1973-1985 (Box 9)
    - Various friends, 1974 (Box 9)
    - First draft, 1973 (Box 9)
  - Sound recordings, 1964-1982
    Interviews with individuals on Herbst
    Conditions Governing Access
    Boxes 20-21 (audiocassettes and microcassettes) and Box 22 (audiotape reels): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Untitled; hi-speed, side 7, undated; 1; 00:37:02; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The tape speed gradually gets faster throughout the program. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104884722)
    - Mary Lloyd, undated; 1; 00:24:10; Static and background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104884730)
    - "Between the Covers", KBOO Radio, Portland, OR, 1985 October 29; 1; 00:29:30; Static can be heard on the tape. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104884748)
    - Ruth Beck, undated; 1; 01:26:07; Static can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104884755)
    - Ellie - KBOO Reading, 1977 April 18; 1; 00:50:04; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104884763)
    - Eleanor Clark & Robert Penn Warren, W. Wardsboro, VT, undated; 1; 00:57:45; Static and a high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. There is silence from 00:54:30 to 00:56:03. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104884771)
      A note found with the audiocassette says: "El. Clark said now that Nixon's down, some people think Alger Hiss should be up."
    - Untitled, undated; 1; 01:02:07; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104884789)
    - Josie Herbst, undated; 1; 01:10:41; Writing on the audiocassette is extremely faded.; Static and a high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. Tape speed quickens at about 00:46:00. Sections of the cassette have been recorded over. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104884797)
    - Elinor Langer, Fairhaven College, 1979 February 23; 1; 01:34:42; Static and a high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104884805)
    - ? Mysterious tape from Iowa trip ?, 1975 Spring; 1; 00:05:44; The program is distorted at times. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104884813)
    - Bucks County Tape, 1975 August; 1; 00:24:18; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104884821)
      Contents include a recap of an interview with Neil and Mary Daniels in Pennsylvania.
    - Untitled, E-5 and F-6, undated; 1; 01:27:44; Static and a high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104884839)
    - [Josephine Herbst] Memorial Service, undated; 1; 00:37:23; The first 37 minutes are recorded at a very low level. There is silence in the audio at about 00:40:00 to 00:41:30. There is a high amount of background noise from 00:37:24 to the end of the tape. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104884847)
    - Andrew Bernhard, side 1 and 2, undated; 1; 01:29:45; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104884854)
    - Andrew Bernhard, side 3 and 4, undated; 1; 01:17:22; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104884862)
    - Untitled, side 8 and 9, undated; 1; 01:07:09; Buzz and a high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104884870)
    - Mary Lloyd two, undated; 1; 01:07:49; The program was recorded at a very low level. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104884888)
    - Untitled, undated; 1; This tape is blank. It has not been digitized. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104884896)
    - JG, Hofstra - Tape 1, undated; 1; 01:01:48; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104884904)
    - NY - New Haven trip notes / Farrell Phillips, undated; 1; 01:03:15; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. There is a gap in audio from about 47:02 to 48:47. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104884912)
      Notes indicate side A useless and side B good.
    - Untitled, undated; 1; 00:10:53; Buzz and a high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. There are several stops and gaps in the recording. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104884920)
    - Becky ?, undated; 1; 00:47:05; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104884938)
    - The Bio-er + The Subject, [Santa Cruz], 1982 March; 1; 01:02:27; Static and a high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104884946)
    - Leslie Hilton-Esta, S. Kunitz, D. Forreu, Julid Older, Alfred Stanley Kunitz observations, Final Trip, 1979 November - 1980 January; 1; 00:47:44; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. There are speed fluctuations at about 47:45 until the end of the tape. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104884953)
    - SP Earth, undated; 1; 00:47:09; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times and was recorded at a very high level. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104884961)
    - The Bio-er + The Subject, Santa Cruz, 1982 March; 1; This microcassette is blank. It has not been digitized. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104884979)
    - JG, Hofstra - Tape 2, 1982 November 6; 1; 00:39:26; Static and buzz can be heard on the tape. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104884987)
    - Untitled, undated; 1; 00:31:17; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104884995)
    - Betty Davis, A + B, 1979 April; 1; 00:44:31; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104885018)
    - Betty Davis, side 3, 1979 April; 1; 00:44:15 (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104885000)
    - "Daydreaming" / Goddard Bio G. talk, 1976 April; 1; 01:02:10; Static and a high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 21, Item barcode 39002104885026)
    - Untitled, undated; 1; 00:29:47; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 21, Item barcode 39002104885034)
    - Women's Guild, undated; 1; 01:01:05 (Box 21, Item barcode 39002104885042)
    - Maxim Lieber, East Hartford, Conn., 1972 July 3; 1; 01:31:53 (Box 21, Item barcode 39002104885059)
    - Visit Ruth Hermann Peck, Bridgehampton, L.I., 1974 August 16-18; 1; 01:24:59; The program is distorted at times. (Box 21, Item barcode 39002104885067)
      Notes include: Jo's text of photo album, Marion, and politics.
      This audiocassette was labeled as YCAL MSS 475_0002.
    - Untitled, undated; 1; This tape is blank. It has not been digitized. (Box 21, Item barcode 39002104885075)
    - Meridel as Donald Duck, end of discussion of Josie and '35 Congress, undated; 1; 00:58:50; The program is recorded at a very low level at times. The tape speed varies throughout the recording. The program is distorted at times. (Box 21, Item barcode 39002104885083)
    - Mary Lloyd / George Lloyd, undated; 1; 00:23:13; Static can be heard on the tape. The program was recorded at a very low level. (Box 21, Item barcode 39002104885091)
    - KATU 2 at 4, at 200 Koin News, undated; 1; 01:03:54; The program is distorted at times. There is silence at about 56:17 to 59:37. (Box 21, Item barcode 39002104885109)
    - Colloquium Series - "The Biographer & The Subject: Aspects of the Biography of Josephine Herbst" - Elinor Langer, 1983 April 5; 1; 00:48:34; There is a high amount of hiss on the tape. (Box 21, Item barcode 39002104885117)
    - Women's Guild, undated; 1; 01:53:20; A high amount of hiss can be heard on the tape. The program was recorded at a very low level at times. (Box 21, Item barcode 39002104885125)
    - Mary Lloyd, Josie Herbst novelist, Chicago, undated; 1; 01:16:11; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 21, Item barcode 39002104885133)
    - I. Meridel Le S. / Donald Duck, undated; 1; 01:29:17; A high amount of background noise and buzz can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. The recording speeds up at the end of the program. (Box 21, Item barcode 39002104885141)
    - ?, undated; 1; 00:16:03; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 21, Item barcode 39002104885158)
    - Continuation of Jo's text of photo album (and comments) / theft of Anne Peroff love letter (Jan. 23, 1937) / Mich. prize winning poet and important stuff! Ruth feels, 1974 August 18; 1; 01:25:07; The program is distorted at times. (Box 21, Item barcode 39002104885174)
    - Jessica [?], 1974; 1; 00:36:17; The program is distorted at times. (Box 21, Item barcode 39002104885182)
      Notes on the audiocassette have worn off and are extremely difficult to read.
    - Conversation Jessie Lloyd O'Conner [regarding] Josie on film, 1976 September 26; 1; 00:13:29; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 21, Item barcode 39002104885190)
    - Josie, Jean G., Betty Hampton and Steve Davis, 1964; 1; 01:00:32; A high amount of background noise and hum can be heard on the tape. (Box 21, Item barcode 39002104885208)
    - Gardner pp 19-32 / Gardner pp 32-46, 1976 April; 1; 01:01:01; Static and a high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 21, Item barcode 39002104885216)
    - Spanish Civil War readings and songs: Studs Terkel, Tom Glazer, Elinor Langer, Bob Colodny; Breasted Hall, Reel 1 (1 of 2 audiocassettes), 1976 May 3; 1; 01:29:38 (Box 21, Item barcode 39002104885224)
    - Spanish Civil War readings and songs: Studs Terkel, Tom Glazer, Elinor Langer, Bob Colodny; Breasted Hall, Reel 2 (2 of 2 audiocassettes), 1976 May 3; 1; 00:16:55; Static can be heard on the tape. (Box 21, Item barcode 39002104885232)
    - Josephine Herbst / James T. Farrell, July 30; 1; 01:52:29; A high amount of background noise can be heard on the tape. There is a gap from 39:00 to 41:39. (Box Portfolio 22, Item barcode 39002104885240)
- Writings and related material, 1968-1994; Series II; 9.5; (10 boxes)
  This series contains drafts, notes, photocopies, correspondence and photograph reproductions created by Langer as part of her writing process. Among the papers are printed material, publicity, and reviews regarding the publication of Langer's book.
  - Notes and typescript preliminary drafts, 1975-1982; 24 (Box 10)
  - Printed material, notes, and typescript drafts, 1974-1994; 16 (Box 11)
  - Typescript drafts, correspondence regarding permissions and interviews, 1968-1984; 29 (Box 12)
  - Photograph reproductions for publication, typescript drafts and page proofs, 1974-1984; 15 (Box 13)
  - Bibliographies and research notes, 1969-1982; 45 (Box 14)
  - Notes, publicity and reviews, 1981-1985; 23 (Box 15)
  - Notes, proofs and draft fragments, publicity and reviews, photograph reproductions for publication, 1974-1985; 35 (Box 16)
  - Notes, photograph reproductions for publication, photocopies of Herbst's writings, 1974-1981; 16 (Box 17)
  - Notes and photocopies, 1973-1984; 9 (Box 18)
  - Reviews, 1984 August-December (Box 19)